Papers of Angela Hutchinson Hammer 1917-1952
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Papers of Angela Hutchinson Hammer 1917-1952
AZ 012
Hammer, Angela Hutchinson
Autobiographical reminiscences, correspondence, and a short story relating to Angela Hammer's life in Arizona.
0.4 linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://www.library.arizona.edu/speccoll
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Angela Hutchison Hammer was Arizona’s Pioneer Newspapers woman. She was born November 30, 1870 in Virginia City, Nevada. She and her parents moved to Picket Post, Arizona, in 1883. Angela earned her teaching certificate in 1889 and taught school in Wickenburg, 1889-90, 1894-1896 and Gila Bend from 1893-1894. She married Joseph S. Hammer in 1896 and had three sons: Louis Joseph Fairfax, William and Marvin. The marriage was dissolved after 8 years. In 1905 Angela bought her first newspaper the Wickenburg Miner. From 1908 to 1910, she worked hard to establish a chain of newspapers in four rapidly growing Arizona mining towns. Angela had her own printing plant in Congress Junction, where she published the Wickenburg Miner, Swansea Times, and Wenden News.
In 1912 she moved her printing plant from Congress Junction to Casa Grande to assist Ted Healey with the publishing of the Casa Grande Bulletin. The Bulletin didn't make it but Angela went on to publish the Casa Grande Dispatch on January 1, 1914. Mrs. Hammer quickly earned a reputation for aggressive, honest reporting and her strong editorial opinions. She used the editorial power of her newspapers to effect social change, order and lawfulness in those early mining towns, women's suffrage, statehood and, later, conservation of ground water and the promotion of dam projects for agricultural irrigation.
In 1925 Mrs. Hammer moved to Phoenix and the established the Messenger Printing Co., operated by her two sons, William and Marvin. That company merged in April 1951 with Arizona Printers Inc., and Mrs. Hammer became a board member of the combined operation.
In 1938 she was appointed by Governor R. C. Stanford to the State Board of Social Security and Welfare, a position she held until 1943. Angela H. Hammer was a member of many professional organizations, including the Phoenix Business and Professional Women's Club, the Phoenix branch of The National League of American Pen Women and the Phoenix Writers Club. She also has the distinction of holding membership in two Halls of Fame in Arizona. The Women's Hall of Fame and the Arizona Newspaper Hall of Fame in 1965.
She died April 9, 1952, and is buried in Phoenix.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 2 series
Series I: Reminiscences 1940-1952
Series II: Correspondence 1917-1952
Scope and Content Note
Autobiographical reminiscences, correspondence, and a short story relating to Mrs. Hammer's life in Arizona. Also includes a pencil sketch of Wickenburg School in 1890, and a photograph of the Messenger Printing Co., Phoenix, ca. 1940-1950.
Access Terms
Frontier and pioneer life--Arizona
American newspapers--Arizona
Journalists--Arizona
Teachers--Arizona--Biography
Women editors--Arizona
Cities and towns--Arizona--History
Public schools--Arizona--Casa Grande--History.
Public schools--Arizona--Wickerw|x History
Wickenburg Miner (Newspaper)--History
Wickenburg (Ariz.)--Newspapers--History
Pinal County (Ariz.)--History
Arizona--History, Local
Container List
- Series I: Reminiscences, 1917-1950
  This series is organized by date.
  - Outlines, chronology, "reminders", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper experience general, survey, notes), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - )Family history, parents, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Childhood: California, Nevada, Arkansas, 1870-1885 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wickenburg and Vulture mine (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Phoenix (Summer vacations), 1870-1885 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Wickenburg (School teaching,Walnut Grove flood), 1889-1891; 1894-1895 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gila Bend (Enterprise school), 1893-1894 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Phoenix California,El Paso, 1896-1903 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wickenburg, Bouse, Congress Junction, 1904-1919? (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Casa Grande (Partially completed MS), 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Casa Grande, Phoenix, 1914-1929 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Depression plans", 1930-1934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Wickenburg Pageant, 1930-1934 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - TV, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Story "The Country editor", undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1917-1952
  This series is arranged by date
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 16)